<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.mmp.Vice</id>
  
  <name>Vice</name>
  <summary>Air Traffic Control Simulator</summary>
  
  <metadata_license>MIT</metadata_license>
  <project_license>AGPL-3.0-only</project_license>
  
  <description>
    <p>Vice is an air traffic control simulator, focused on TRACON. It presents a STARS-like interface, but with simulated traffic and other controllers. It also supports multiple users, where each person controls a different position at a facility.</p>
    <p>Vice supports departure and arrival control scenarios in numerous TRACONs and ATCT/TRACONs, currently: A11, A80, A90, AAC, ABE, ABQ, AGS, ALB, ASE, AUS, AVL, BGR, BHM, BIL, BNA, BOI, BTV, BUF, C90, CHS, CID, CLE, CLT, COS, CPR, D01, D10, D21, DAB, EWR, F11, GSO, GSP, GTF, I90, IND, JAX, L30, M98, MCI, MDT, MIA, MKE, N90, NCT, OKC, P31, P50, P80, PCT, PHL, PIT, PVD, PWM, R90, RDU, S46, S56, SAV, SBA, SBN, SCT, SDF, SGF, SYR, TPA, and Y90. New scenarios are regularly added.</p>
  </description>

  <developer id="io.github.mmp">
    <name>Matt Pharr</name>
  </developer>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.mmp.Vice.desktop</launchable>

  <url type="homepage">https://pharr.org/vice/</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/mmp/vice</url>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://i.imgur.com/ZeqnWqm.png</image>
      <caption>Boston Approach Consolidated</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://i.imgur.com/XfmZKcs.png</image>
      <caption>Scenario Selection Menu</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  
  <content_rating type="oars-1.0">
    <content_attribute id="social-chat">intense</content_attribute>
  </content_rating>
  
  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#b9d6ed</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#004b71</color>
  </branding>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.13.3" date="2025-12-29">
      <url type="details">https://pharr.org/vice/#release-0.13.3</url>
      <description>
	<p>Adds new scenarios, updates to STARS/ERAM, and bug fixes</p>
	<ul>
	  <li>New scenarios: PCT consolidated (Ketan K), MYR (Jud Lopez)</li>
	  <li>Scenario updates: A80, C90, D01, D10, DAB, F11, JAX, MKE, ZJX (Jud Lopez), SAV (manaphy), DelRey, SNA, P50, L30 (Ketan K), ISP, ZNY Area D (Ryan G), P80 (Mike Fries), BOS (radarcontacto)</li>
	</ul>
	<p>STARS updates:</p>
	  <ul>
	    <li>Added support for changing position consolidation during the sim: [multifunc]1A1B+[enter], etc.</li>
	    <li>ATPA improvements: added enable/disable commands, improved various details.</li>
	    <li>Added support for middle-click-drag to move lists.</li>
	    <li>Also, middle clicking anywhere that's not inside a list or on a track shows the bounds of all visible lists.</li>
	    <li>Fixed bug with DCB spinners not disabling after a click.</li>
	  </ul>
	<p>ERAM updates:</p>
	<ul>
	  <li>Added CRR (continuous range readout).</li>
	  <li>Added <code>.drawroute</code></li>
	</ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>


</component>
