<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.mmp.Vice</id>
  
  <name>Vice</name>
  <summary>Air Traffic Control Simulator</summary>
  
  <metadata_license>MIT</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-only</project_license>
  
  <description>
    <p>Vice is an air traffic control simulator, focused on TRACON. It presents a STARS-like interface, but with simulated traffic and other controllers. It also supports multiple users, where each person controls a different position at a facility.</p>
    <p>Vice supports departure and arrival control scenarios in numerous TRACONs and ATCT/TRACONs, currently: A11, A80, A90, AAC, ABE, ABQ, AGS, ALB, ASE, AUS, AVL, BGR, BHM, BIL, BNA, BOI, BTV, BUF, C90, CHS, CID, CLE, CLT, COS, CPR, D01, D10, D21, DAB, EWR, F11, GSO, GSP, GTF, I90, IND, JAX, L30, M98, MCI, MDT, MIA, MKE, N90, NCT, OKC, P31, P50, P80, PCT, PHL, PIT, PVD, PWM, R90, RDU, S46, S56, SAV, SBA, SBN, SCT, SDF, SGF, SYR, TPA, and Y90. New scenarios are regularly added.</p>
  </description>

  <developer id="io.github.mmp">
    <name>Matt Pharr</name>
  </developer>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.mmp.Vice.desktop</launchable>

  <url type="homepage">https://pharr.org/vice/</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/mmp/vice</url>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://i.imgur.com/ZeqnWqm.png</image>
      <caption>Boston Approach Consolidated</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://i.imgur.com/r8mlorU.png</image>
      <caption>New York Center Area C</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://i.imgur.com/XfmZKcs.png</image>
      <caption>Scenario Selection Menu</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  
  <content_rating type="oars-1.0" />
  
  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#b9d6ed</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#004b71</color>
  </branding>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.14.4" date="2026-06-16">
      <url type="details">https://pharr.org/vice/#release-0.14.4</url>
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>New scenarios: ZBW Nantucket 17 (Ryan G), M03 (manaphy, Ryan G), ZJX West combined (manaphy), PBI (Ketan K), ORF (Ryan H)</li>
          <li>Scenario updates: BOI (Elliot B), MIA, ZJX (manaphy), PCT, NCT (Ketan K), ZNY (Ryan G), BTV (EkimWasHere), BOS (radarcontacto), I90 (Ethan Hawes), Y90 (CiceroIsBack)</li>
          <li>Pronunciation fixes: I90 (Ethan Hawes)</li>
          <li>Added support for scenario briefings (only JFK and LGA for now)</li>
          <li>Improve handling of arrival airport winds on final approach (radarcontacto)</li>
          <li>Fixed bug where aircraft would speed up after missing an approach intercept</li>
          <li>STT: Fixed handling of &quot;maintain best forward speed&quot;</li>
          <li>STT: Added support for &quot;cross (fix) at or below (altitude)&quot;</li>
          <li>Visual approaches: Fixed bugs where aircraft cleared for approaches would still report the field in sight</li>
          <li>Visual approaches: Fixed descent profile for aircraft cleared for visual approaches</li>
          <li>STARS: Fixed bug where aircraft on visual approaches could have unwanted MSAW alerts</li>
          <li>STARS: Fixed bugs with cursor disappearing at inopportune times</li>
          <li>ERAM: Fixed bugs with drawing map annotations and map brightness handling</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.3" date="2026-05-08">
      <url type="details">https://pharr.org/vice/#release-0.14.3</url>
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>New scenarios: EUG, MFR (Mike Fries)</li>
          <li>Scenario updates: ZNY, Y90 (Ryan G), SCT (Ketan K), ZJX, F11, N90 (manaphy), MIA (Gecko)</li>
          <li>Updated radio static/muffling model (radarcontacto)</li>
          <li>Added support for visual approaches (Jordan Williams)</li>
          <li>Fixed bugs with localizer intercept and approach clearance</li>
          <li>Fixed bug where aircraft would sometimes spontaneously leave holds (Jud Lopez)</li>
          <li>Handle &quot;at or above/at or below&quot; speed restrictions more reasonably (don't treat them all as &quot;at&quot;)</li>
          <li>Added support for &quot;join the approach&quot; for non-ILS/LOC approaches</li>
          <li>Fixed a few bugs with &quot;at {fix}, cleared straight in {approach}&quot;</li>
          <li>Added &quot;after {fix}, climb/descend and maintain {altitude}&quot;</li>
          <li>Added &quot;after {fix}, reduce/maintain/increase {speed}&quot;</li>
          <li>Added &quot;speed {speed1} until {fix1}, then {speed2} until {fix2}, then {speed3}&quot;, etc.</li>
          <li>Added &quot;cross {fix} {miles} miles {direction} of {fix}&quot;</li>
          <li>Added &quot;good rate&quot; for climbs/descents: &quot;descend and maintain 3,000, good rate through 5,000&quot;, etc.</li>
          <li>Added optional altitudes to expedite to: &quot;expedite through 5,000&quot;, etc.</li>
          <li>Added &quot;cross {miles} DME at {altitude/speed}&quot; instruction for visual approaches</li>
          <li>Aircraft now ask for an altitude if vectored off an arrival without being assigned one (Michael Knight)</li>
          <li>Added UI option to force (realistic) square windows for STARS/ERAM radar displays</li>
          <li>Fixed bug where aircraft would be at bogus altitudes/speeds after prespawn</li>
          <li>ERAM: Added ALTIM SET and WX REPORT floating windows, including AR/WR keyboard commands (Michael Knight)</li>
          <li>ERAM: Fixed bug where far-away fixes weren't known for control instructions</li>
          <li>STARS: Added support for &quot;Create interfacility VFR flight plan from active local track&quot;</li>
          <li>STARS: GI and ATIS text in the SSA list is managed by the server (so updates are shared among controllers)</li>
          <li>STARS: Allow scrolling the DCB if it's too big to fit the screen (Jud Lopez)</li>
          <li>Facility engineering: Support &quot;at or above/at or below&quot; speed restrictions</li>
          <li>Facility engineering: Added &quot;flight_type&quot; for overflights so aircraft flight types can be specified as &quot;departure&quot; or &quot;arrival&quot; (rather than always being &quot;overflight&quot;)</li>
          <li>Facility engineering: Added support for actions at waypoints until reaching an altitude or DME from a fix, e.g. &quot;FIX/h090@a30/h120&quot; departs fix at an 090 heading until reaching 3,000', then flies 120.</li>
          <li>Facility engineering: Candidate visual approach courses can be specified in scenarios as &quot;type&quot;: &quot;Visual&quot; (we now use &quot;ChartedVisual&quot; for charted visual approaches)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.2" date="2026-03-29">
      <url type="details">https://pharr.org/vice/#release-0.14.2</url>
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>New scenario: LBB (Gecko), ZNY E/F (Ryan G), TYS (Jake Magee / manaphy), FAT (Ketan K), ZJX 88 (manaphy)</li>
          <li>Scenario updates: NCT, SCT, ZLA (Ketan K), N90 (manaphy, Ryan G), MIA (Gecko), ZNY, PHL, BOS (Ryan G), BOS, DCA (radarcontacto), I90 (Ketan K), ZJX (manaphy)</li>
          <li>Updated to AIRAC 260319 (Ketan K)</li>
          <li>Adjusted radio noise simulation to reduce muffling of pilot responses</li>
          <li>Added pin in subwindow top bars to control whether they stay on top of the main radar scope window (all are pinned by default)</li>
          <li>Flight simulation: Added &quot;left/right direct {fix}&quot; instruction (LDFIX, RDFIX if you're not using stt)</li>
          <li>Flight simulation: Improved pilot initial contact messages to include SIDs/STARs, altitude/speed restrictions, assigned headings, etc.</li>
          <li>Flight simulation: Aircraft will continue to descend after reaching the end of a STAR</li>
          <li>Flight simulation: Fixed some bugs with meeting altitude restrictions on STARs</li>
          <li>STT: &quot;Negative, ...&quot; actually causes the aircraft that misheard the instruction to ignore it.</li>
          <li>STT: &quot;Negative, (updated instructions)&quot; is allowed when an aircraft reads back the wrong instructions (i.e., the callsign isn't required).</li>
          <li>STT: If a VFR calls in with a request, replying &quot;(callsign), XYZ approach&quot; is treated as &quot;go ahead&quot;</li>
          <li>STT: Added support for &quot;expect direct (fix)&quot; / &quot;expect to rejoin the arrival at (fix)&quot;</li>
          <li>STT: Fixed some issues with &quot;at (fix), cleared (approach)&quot;</li>
          <li>Facility engineering: Added support for per-area and per-controller &quot;altimeters&quot; lists</li>
          <li>Facility engineering: Added &quot;cleared_altitude&quot; for arrivals/overflights: this is like &quot;cleared_altitude&quot; for departures--aircraft try to get to that altitude when able, but obey altitude restrictions in their route while doing so.</li>
          <li>Facility engineering: When specifying routes, you can now use &quot;/t&quot; to specify departing a fix on a track heading, and &quot;/lt&quot; and &quot;/rt&quot; with a heading to specify a left/right turn to the given track heading.</li>
          <li>Facility engineering: When specifying routes, you can use &quot;/ld&quot; to specify to turn left when proceeding to the next fix, and similarly for &quot;/rd&quot; for turning right.</li>
          <li>STARS: improved realism of datablock clock phases, add FE controls to specify cycle and lengths</li>
          <li>Added pipeline to ingest and use historical TFRs (alongside wx)</li>
          <li>Facility engineering: Improved restriction area specification in configs: RA numbers are now part of the specification, and auto-RAs-from-TFRs can be disabled</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.1" date="2026-03-09">
      <url type="details">https://pharr.org/vice/#release-0.14.1</url>
      <description>
        <ul>
          <li>New scenario: ZJX Consolidated (Jake Magee)</li>
          <li>Text to speech now runs locally on your computer rather than in the cloud</li>
          <li>Lots of small improvements to speech-to-text</li>
          <li>Flight strips have been reworked; right click to get a menu to push them to the next controller</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Long requested: you can actually move sub-windows outside of the main window</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The flight strip and messages windows are now sub-windows and now its just the radar scope in the main window</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Added ATIS simulation: see the ATIS/METAR tab in the scenario info window for what's current</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Aircraft will call in with the current ATIS; if it's changed and they call in with the old one, STT supports "information X is now current," "advise you have information X", etc., or with the keyboard you can issue the command <code>ATIS/X</code> to tell them X is current</li>
        </ul>
        <p>ERAM updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added support for giving aircraft speeds in mach (Michael Trokel)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.14.0" date="2026-02-06">
      <url type="details">https://pharr.org/vice/#release-0.14.0</url>
      <description>
        <p>Adds text to speech, scenario updates, and other minor improvements</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added speech-to-text support (Michael Trokel / Matt P)</li>
          <li>New Scenarios: ZLC Area C (JY_SUPn't), ZJX 30 (Jake Magee), CVG (manaphy), ZDV Area 3 (Andrew S)</li>
          <li>Scenario updates: BOS, ACK, MHT (radarcontacto), P50 (Ketan K), COS (Andrew S), BGR (Ryan G), M98 (Logan S), F11, ZJX 50 (Jud Lopez), DAB, F11 (Michael Knight), MIA (Gecko)</li>
          <li>Added search box to filter scenarios</li>
          <li>Improved pilot readbacks to be more natural / cohesive</li>
          <li>VFRs are better about not flying into terrain</li>
          <li>Added "at fix, intercept the localizer" command: <code>AFIX/I</code></li>
          <li>Fixed bug with multi-controller scenarios where controllers could be locked out of issuing aircraft commands.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>STARS updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fixed bug where interfacility handoffs would get a FORMAT error</li>
          <li>Fixed keyboard input for DCB button values (e.g. RANGE)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>ERAM updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added QF and QU commands</li>
          <li>Added tearoffs, cursors, and clock</li>
          <li>Added HSF data</li>
          <li>Switched tertiary/primary mouse clicks to primary/secondary</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.13.3" date="2025-12-29">
      <url type="details">https://pharr.org/vice/#release-0.13.3</url>
      <description>
        <p>Adds new scenarios, updates to STARS/ERAM, and bug fixes</p>
        <ul>
          <li>New scenarios: PCT consolidated (Ketan K), MYR (Jud Lopez)</li>
          <li>Scenario updates: A80, C90, D01, D10, DAB, F11, JAX, MKE, ZJX (Jud Lopez), SAV (manaphy), DelRey, SNA, P50, L30 (Ketan K), ISP, ZNY Area D (Ryan G), P80 (Mike Fries), BOS (radarcontacto)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>STARS updates:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>Added support for changing position consolidation during the sim: [multifunc]1A1B+[enter], etc.</li>
            <li>ATPA improvements: added enable/disable commands, improved various details.</li>
            <li>Added support for middle-click-drag to move lists.</li>
            <li>Also, middle clicking anywhere that's not inside a list or on a track shows the bounds of all visible lists.</li>
            <li>Fixed bug with DCB spinners not disabling after a click.</li>
          </ul>
        <p>ERAM updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added CRR (continuous range readout).</li>
          <li>Added <code>.drawroute</code></li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>


</component>
